American Jewish Congress Collection 0007.001.006b
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
American Jewish Congress
1940-1999
0007.001.006b
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
2.0 Cubic feet 3 Boxes, Photographs, oversized materials
The American Jewish Congress was founded in 1918 in response to Jewish concerns arising at the time of World War I. The AJC has remained an advocate for Zionism as well as developing programs to fight racism and all forms discrimination. The Hartford chapter and its Women's Division were formed in the 1930s; they merged in 1982.
When the Hartford Chapter formed, they saw themselves as "a permanent body of Jewish organizations, to carry out the work of the [C]ongress in this city...", and they solicited the membership of and delegates from each of the other extant Jewish groups in town. The Hartford Chapter was particularly active during the turbulent 1960s and 70s.
Although the Hartford Chapter is no longer active, the national organization continues to advocate for continuity of American Jewish culture, the survival of Israel, women's rights, and civil rights for all citizens.
Scope and Contents note
The material in this collection dates from the late 1940s-1980s. During the 1940s Israel was founded, the Civil Rights movement began, and American Jews began to react to the legacy of the Holocaust. Later materials deal with the continuing Arab- Israeli conflict, issues of separation of church and state in the United States, and the emergence of hate groups and cults.
Wagner, Jerry, Law, Honorable Judge; American Jewish Congress; Board of Directors; Connecticut Council; Members/Membership
- Series I: Connecticut Council -- Hartford Chapter
  - Connecticut Council/Incorporation, undated (Box 1)
  - Connecticut District/Election, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Board of Directors/Executive committees, 1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Board of Directors/Members, undated (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Board of Directors/Minutes, 10/1954 - 3/1966, 1954-1966 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Membership/Lists, 1950s, 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Membership/Lists, 1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Membership/Lists, 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Membership/Lists, undated (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Membership/Miscellaneous, 1960s-1970s, 1960-1979 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Men's Division, 1950s, 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Merger of General Division and Women's Division, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Minutes, 1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Newspaper clippings/Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Programs, 1950s, 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Programs, 1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Programs, 1970s-1990s, 1970-1999 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Programs/Ephemera, 1950s-1960s, 1950-1969 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Publications/Newspaper Column by Dr. Sidney Rafal, 1952-53, 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Wagner, Jerry/Correspondence, 1950s, 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Wagner, Jerry/Correspondence, 1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Wagner, Jerry/Correspondence, 1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Wagner, Jerry/Correspondence and memos/Commission on Law Social Action and Urban Affairs, 1970s, undated (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Wagner, Jerry/Correspondence and memos/Miscellaneous, 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Chapter/Newsletters, 1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 1)
- Series II: Hartford Chapter/Women's Division
  - Hartford Chapter/Women's Division/Board of Directors/Members, undated (Box 2)
  - Hartford Chapter/Women's Division/Board of Directors/Minutes, 1949-1950 (Box 2)
  - Hartford Chapter/Women's Division/Board of Directors/Subcommittees, 1940s, 1940-1949 (Box 2)
  - Hartford Chapter/Women's Division/Commission on Community Inter-relations Experimental Institute on Incident Control, 1948, undated (Box 2)
  - Hartford Chapter/Women's Division/Correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 2)
  - Hartford Chapter/Women's Division/Hartford Town Meeting on "Educating the Jewish Child," 1948 (Box 2)
  - Hartford Chapter/Women's Division/Jewish Book Festival, undated (Box 2)
  - Hartford Chapter/Women's Division/Meeting Programs, undated (Box 2)
  - Hartford Chapter/Women's Division/Meeting Program Suggestions, undated (Box 2)
  - Hartford Chapter/Women's Division/Members and Membership, undated (Box 2)
  - Hartford Chapter/Women's Division/Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2)
  - Hartford Chapter/Women's Division/Miscellaneous/Background Information Collected by Emma Cohen/Race relations, Zionism, and Anti-Semitism, undated (Box 2)
  - Hartford Chapter/Women's Division/Newsletter, 1948-1950 (Box 2)
  - Hartford Chapter/Women's Division/Reports, undated (Box 2)
  - Hartford Chapter/Women's Division/Scrapbook, 1948-1950 (Box 2)
  - Hartford Chapter/Women's Division/Scrapbook, 1950-1951 (Box 2)
  - Members/Membership Lists, 1950s, 1950-1959 (Box 2)
  - Members/Membership Lists, 1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 2)
  - Members/Membership Lists, 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 2)
  - Members/Membership Lists, undated (Box 2)
- Series III: National Organization
  - National Organization/Advisory Bulletins, undated (Box 3)
  - National Organization/Commission on Law and Social Action/Minutes, 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 3)
  - National Organization/Commission on Law and Social Action/Newsletter, 1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 3)
  - National Organization/Commission on Law, Social Action, and Urban Affairs/Report, 1965-1970s, 1965-1979 (Box 3)
  - National Organization/Commission on Law, Social Action, and Urban Affairs/Members, undated (Box 3)
  - National Organization/Ephemera, undated (Box 3)
  - National Organization/History, undated (Box 3)
  - National Organization/Memoranda, 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 3)
  - National Organization/Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3)
  - National Organization/News releases, 1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 3)
  - National Organization/Publications, undated (Box 3)
- Photographs
  - Filed under Photographs/Organizations/American Jewish Congress, undated
- Oversized Materials
  - Connecticut Council Charter, 1956 (photocopy in Connecticut Council folder)
  - Jewish Book Festival Poster, 1947 (photocopy in Hartford Chapter/Women's Division/ Jewish Book Festival folder)